<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for the Protestants of Ireland in a brief narrative of the late revolutions in that kingdom, and an account of the present state thereof.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16309</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11732775</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11732775</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48411</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 482:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for the Protestants of Ireland in a brief narrative of the late revolutions in that kingdom, and an account of the present state thereof.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1688-1689.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48411:1"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE PROTESTANTS of IRELAND. In a Brief NARRATIVE OF THE LATE REVOLUTIONS In that KINGDOM, AND An Account of the PRESENT STATE Thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <l>——Quaeque ipſe miſerrima vidi,</l>
               <l>Et quorum pars magna fui,——</l>
            </q>
            <p>Licenſed and Entered according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwel,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48411:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48411:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY FOR THE PROTESTANTS OF IRELAND,</head>
            <head type="sub">In a brief Narrative of the Late Revolutions in that KINGDOM, and an Account of the Preſent STATE thereof.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am urged by the incentives of Love and Gratitude for the many obligations you have laid upon me, and by the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of my own promiſe, to render you an Account of the late Revolutions in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and to lay before you a true Scheme of the preſent condition of that miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and forlorn Country. In the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance whereof if I be neceſſitated to utter ſome unwelcome Truths; I beſpeak your Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to believe, it does not proceed from any deſign of a malicious Reflection, but from that irreſiſtable Force that naturally attends a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48411:3"/>faithful Narration. And becauſe the miſery of Exile and Deſertion is ſenſibly aggravated by their cruel and unequal cenſure, who neither underſtand the cauſe, nor pity the effects of ſo fatal a dereliction of our Eſtates and Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but ſeverely upbraid us with an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, timorous and unneceſſary Flight; it will not be poſſible to obviate ſuch ill ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cavils, or to deſcribe the preſent face of Affairs, without a Retroſpect on the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of things as they formerly appeared.</p>
            <p>While <hi>Charles</hi> the Second ſway'd the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; though the Papiſts were too much coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced and indulg'd; and many hardſhips placed on the Proteſtants, eſpecially in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Act of Settlement, yet by the favour of Heaven upon the extraordinary Fertility of the Land, <hi>Ireland</hi> was under very auſpicious circumſtances: The Church Flouriſhed, Trade Increaſed, the Cities and Towns were every Year inlarged with new Additions, the Country In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched and Beautified with Houſes and Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Farms were loaden with Stock, and ready and quick Markets there were to vent them: The Laws had a free and uninterrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed courſe, and a ſtanding Army was ſo far
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48411:3"/>from being a Terrour, that they were the comfort and ſecurity of the people: In a Word, Peace, Wealth, and Plenty were become univerſal and epidemical, and all things conſpired to a generous Emulation with our Mother and Neighbour, <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But no ſooner did this bright Sun ſet, and a new One appear'd in the Firmament, but Clouds and Vapours, Storms and Tempeſts aroſe in our Horizon, which have ſince broke out in trouble and confuſion, not like to be ſettled and appeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but in a general deſolation, and depopulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole Kingdome. Indeed at firſt we were flatter'd with ſome hopes of a calm Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by the arrival of the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> and his eſtabliſhment in the Supream command; but his Commiſſion was ſtinted, his Authority far ſhort of what was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to his Predeceſſors in that Government, and Colonel <hi>Richard Talbot</hi> (newly advanced to the ominous Title of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>) openly and impudently appear'd his Comptroller, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor; moſt unjuſtly and preſumptuouſly aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a power to purge the Army, to deveſt the Officers of their Commiſſions, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band thouſands of Stout, well trained Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48411:4"/>deſpoiling them of the very Coats they before paid for, and turning them off Naked, and Bare, to beg, and ſeek their Livelihood, treating them with great Barbarity, and in a jeering and ſcornful manner, giving out, that he muſt have the whole Army of one Size, <hi>i.e.</hi> to be modelliſed and meaſured by the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of <hi>Rome,</hi> and no Man to receive pay from a popiſh King, but he that openly gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up to the avowed profeſſion of Popery. Thus was an Army (not to be excell'd, for their Number, by any Army in <hi>Europe</hi>) bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without a Rout, ſome hundreds of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Officers arbitrarily turn'd out, without the ſatisfaction of aſſigning any Cauſe; and in their Rooms notorious Rebels and Murtherers or the Sons and Off ſpring of ſuch, placed; the Troops and Companies filled with Thieves, Tories, Robbers, and Goal-birds By which Act, as the Inſolency and Inhumanity of the Papiſts was palpably diſcover'd; ſo the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, ſubmiſſion, and non-reſiſtence of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants was evident to the World, by their patient undergoing this Martyrdom in their Fortunes. Soon after that Noble Earl was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, whoſe Adminiſtration was much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliſh'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48411:4"/>by the prevalent party, becauſe ſo grateful to the Proteſtants (to accompany whoſe departure, and to avoid the Tyranny of him that was to follow, 1500 Families de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted <hi>Dublin</hi>) To him ſucceeded the inglori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> in his Morals and Atheiſt, in his profeſſion a Bigot, an egregious Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, and if not a Coward, one over-careful of his own ſafety; a lover of himſelf without a Rival: From whoſe entrance we may dare the Calamities and Deſtruction of the Proteſtant Religion, and of the Britiſh Intereſt in <hi>Ireland.</hi> For having at firſt cull'd, and afterward quite changed the Army, metamorphoſing Mantles into Red Coats, Brogues into Jack-Boots, and Cow-Boys into Captains; he diſperſed his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Legions among all the Towns and Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; where the Name of the Iriſh Granadeers became as formidable, as the French Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons. Next he proceeded to reform the Courts and civil Liſt; diſplacing the Privy-Counſellors, the Judges ſuperſeding the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace, turning out the Sheriffs, and changeing the Officers imployed in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Revenue: Conſtituting in their Rooms the moſt inconſiderable varlets, Men of no Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48411:5"/>Underſtanding, or Eſtate, of no skill in the Laws, or Intereſt in their Country. It was too ſoon for him to Attacque the Church, to invade the Biſhopwricks, or eject the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; but in every City and great Town, he erected Maſs-houſes, re-edify'd the Frieries, made Popiſh coadjutors to the Chaplains of every Regiment, and let looſe a ſwarm of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits and Regulars to infeſt the land: And <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Manby</hi> Dean of <hi>Derry,</hi> having apoſtatiſed from the Religion he was bred in, degraded himſelf from his Function, and degenerated into a Lay-man, yet obtain'd a Patent to injoy the Revenues of the Deanery; and all vacant Biſhopwricks and other Church Dignities were ſequeſter'd and apply'd to the maintenace of the Popiſh Clergy. To compleat the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophes, a <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> or a <hi>Scire facias</hi> was iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued to every City, and Corporation thro' the Kingdom, whereof ſome tamely ſubmitted to a ſurrender, others were condemned upon a <hi>Nihil dicit;</hi> while ſuch as pleaded, and defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Right, had no other return for their Toil and Expences, but a ſcornful publication of a partial and illegal Sentence agreed on and determin'd in the Cabal, before the hearing in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48411:5"/>the Court. A new Charter was ſent to <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and none made Aldermen or Burgeſſes there, but the Sons and Deſcendants of notorious rank Rebels. But leaſt the Hereticks ſhould grow ſturdy, and be in a Capacity to defend themſelves againſt the next Maſſacre, a Proclamation was Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, Requiring all the Officers of the Militia, both Horſe and Foot, forthwith to deliver in to the next Magazine all their Arms; and by this knack, all thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (for no other were of the Militia) were left naked and diſarm'd: Soon after the Juſtices of the Peace in the ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were required to take up all Arms from ſuch as did not come to Church, and to render them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the next Stores; (and by this Trick all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters were left utterly defenſeleſs.)</p>
            <p>And now Popery began to be triumphant, the Lord Deputy and his Privy-Council, (excepting a very few) the Lord Chancellor, and all the Judges, (except three) the Attorney General and the Kings Serjeants, the Juſtices of the Peace, and Sheriffs in each County (except in ſuch Places where no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts were to be had,) all violent, and eager Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion: The Maſs pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly Celebrated in every Town; the Fryers marching in their Habits undiſturbed; the Army reform'd to their own Cue, no Man Countenanced,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48411:6"/>or made a Candidate for any Preferment, but he that truckled to the See of <hi>rome;</hi> the Charters of all Cities, Towns, and Corporations taken away, or condemn'd, and ignorant, indigent, ſcandalous and mean Perſons obtruded upon them. Titles to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates began to be queſtion'd, and ſome unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments given; and what elſe could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, when Judges, Jurors, and Sheriffs, were all of one Stamp? The Proteſtants were daily abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and perſecuted upon Sham Plots, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had an Exiſtence or Foundation, but in the Heads of their malicious Accuſers; and ſeveral Gentlemen were Impriſon'd, Indicted, and Try'd for their Lives. And <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> was heard to ſay to his Countrymen, (and as is reported, by direction from his Lord and Maſter) You have now the Sword in your Hands, the King has given you your own Country to be the Refuge of Catholicks, keep it now you have it, and never ſuffer the damn'd Hereticks to poſſeſs it again.</p>
            <p>In this Poſture of Affairs, was it not high time for the Proteſtants to look about them? to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult their ſafety, and by a timely Removal, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void thoſe imminent Dangers that threatned them. They began indeed to be under dreadful Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſuch as wiſely foreſaw the approaching Miſeries, and were in a Capacity to do it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48411:6"/>themſelves, their Families and Effects into <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> by which means ſo great an Obſtruction was made to the Circulation of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that there follow'd a general decay of Trade through the Kingdom; the Tenants were render'd unable to pay their Rents, and the Landlords to ſubſiſt. Nevertheleſs, in all the Towns and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties there were Multitudes, who couragiouſly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to abide the Brunt, and with a patient Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to expect a Day of Redemption from the Slavery whereunto they were ſubjected, reſolving to follow the Fate of <hi>England,</hi> or hoping for ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Relief from them. In the mean time the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> having a tender regard to the gaſping Condition of the Proteſtant Religion, and condeſcending to aſſiſt the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>England</hi> in the their Reſcue from Popery, Slavery and Arbitrary Power; the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> publickly gave out threatning Speeches, that if the Prince did ſend any Forces thither, he would raiſe and arm all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> from 16. to 60. and leave all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to their Mercy. This proved a new and amazing Terror to the Proteſtants; they plainly ſaw, that if any Forces came from <hi>England,</hi> to call the Papiſts to Account, or to ſupport them, their Lives would be made a Sacrifice to the Fury and Revenge of the Enemy; and that if none came to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48411:7"/>their Aſſiſtance, they remain'd hourly expoſed to Rapine, Maſſacre, and Murder: this terrible Two-edged Conſideration took ſuch Impreſſion on them, that abundance of Men Women and Children withdrew themſelves, and abandon'd the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>But about the beginning of <hi>December</hi> laſt a Letter was found, without a Subſcription, directed to the Earl of <hi>Mont-Alexander,</hi> giving him a friendly warning to take heed to himſelf, and poſitively a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verring a determinate Deſign to Maſſacre all the Proteſtants through the Kingdom, Man, Woman, and Child, and this to be perpetrated preciſely on the Ninth of <hi>December:</hi> Copies of this Letter were immediately tranſmitted to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and diſperſed in all the adjacent Counties; and it is as incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to comprehend, as it is impoſſible to expreſs, what Operation this had on the Minds of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who being either Eye-witneſſes of the horrid Cruelties committed by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in the laſt Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, without the leaſt relenting Compaſſion to Age, or Sex; or having received an indlible Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of their Barbarous Actions, from ſuch as were Sufferers, or Spectators of them; they could by no Conſideration or Arguments be rally'd into any Aſſurance, or be perſwaded to adventure their ſafety under an armed Power, or continue among
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48411:7"/>thoſe, whoſe Principles diſpoſe them to the utter Extirpation of ſuch as they account Hereticks. Hereupon a vaſt number of People in great Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation removed into <hi>England</hi> with their Families, (eſpecially from about <hi>Dublin</hi>) leaving their Goods and Houſhold-ſtuff behind them. With ſome it had a contrary Effect, and generally through the Province of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> the Inhabitants whereof began upon this Alarm to ſtand upon their Guard, and to keep ſtrong Wards and Watches, reſolving nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fly, nor be ſurpriſed; though many things (not known in other Parts) contributed to their Conviction of the Reality of the intended Maſſacre; as the voluntary Confeſſions of certain Prieſts in the County of <hi>Donegal,</hi> who warn'd their Friends ſecretly to depart, becauſe there was a general Maſſacre deſign'd; that the Prieſts were againſt it, but had been over-voted by the Fryers. The Evidence given to a Juſtice of the Peace in the County of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> that one of their Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular Deans was buying up Horſes and Arms, and he declared, that within two or three Years paſt he had laid out 500. <hi>l.</hi> in buying Arms, and that he had beſpoke as many Iron Chains to be Reins for Bridles, as would ſerve Sixty Horſe. (one of which Chains five yards long was deliver'd to the ſaid Juſtice by the Smith that made it) The Words
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48411:8"/>ſpoken by Father <hi>Daly,</hi> Guardian of the Fryery at <hi>Armagh,</hi> who (when he heard that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was to land in <hi>England</hi>) ſaid publickly, that they might thank their Devil of a King for this, for is he had deſtroyed all the Proteſtants when it was in his Power, they had not now call'd in the <hi>Dutch.</hi> But above all, the Attempt of the Papiſts to poſſeſs <hi>London-Derry,</hi> at that very nick of time, turned the Suſpicion into a confident Perſwaſion of the Truth of what was reported. <hi>London-Derry</hi> was then (by the Mercy of God, and the Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the Deputy) without any Garriſon at all in it, the Soldiers being a little before tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon the Expedition into <hi>England;</hi> and it falling ſo out, that upon the very day when a Copy of the above-mention'd Letter was ſent to that City, (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>7th.</hi> of <hi>December</hi>) the Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> with a numerous Party of Highlanders and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> was on his March to Poſſeſs and Command that Place; the Inhabitants looked upon the Advance of ſo many Papiſts on the <hi>7th.</hi> day, to be the Prologue to the Tragedy, intended to be acted on the <hi>9th.</hi> day, and judging, that if they were once admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, all the <hi>Ulſter</hi> and <hi>Conaght Iriſh</hi> might draw thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from thence diffuſe themſelves through the Province, and with great Facility exterminate all the Proteſtants, they (by the Advice of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48411:8"/>in the Neighbourhood) ſhut their Gates, and kept them out, and by his Conduct defended the Place, till a Proteſtant Garriſon was ſettled in it.</p>
            <p>And now the Deputy began to exert his Art, as before he had manifeſted his Tyrannical and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped Authority; for, conſidering that <hi>London-Derry</hi> was out of the Papiſts hands, and that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>Ulſter</hi> were very numerous, he began to cajole and flatter them, for he ſecretly gave out Commiſſions for raiſing of Thirty Regiments; and having Circumvented the Lord <hi>Mountjoy</hi> with ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pretences of Moderation and Peace, and prevail'd with him to go on a Mock Embaſſy to King <hi>James,</hi> then in <hi>France,</hi> he condeſcended to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Articles, which carry'd a ſhew of Mildneſs and Equity, but really were only a Mask to cover his Deſigns, and to amuſe the People; and they were to this Effect. <hi>1ſt.</hi> That no more Forces ſhould be raiſed, nor more Arms deliver'd out of the Stores. <hi>2dly.</hi> That the new Levies ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd <hi>3dly.</hi> That no Forces ſhould be ſent into <hi>Ulſter. 4thly.</hi> That no Nobleman, or Gentlemans Houſe ſhould be made a Garriſon, againſt his Will: Which Stipulations the Deputy heartily ſwore to, and aſſured by many direful Imprecations. No ſooner was the Lord <hi>Mountjoy</hi> gone (who was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48411:9"/>made the meſſenger of his own Fate, and carry'd <hi>Bellerophon</hi>'s Letters with him) but the Deputy proceeded to form a new Army, and gave out Commiſſions for many Regiments of Horſe, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, and Foot, to he number of 40000. Men, without any other Warrant, than a bare Letter from his King; empty'd all the Stores and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines, and furniſh'd the Soldiers with competent Arms, incouraging the Women and Boys, and the whole Rabble of People to provide Skenes and Half-Pikes, and to live upon the Plunder of the Proteſtants; and having no Pay to give among the new Levies, each Captain undertook to give Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence to his Men in Beef and Meal for three Months; and this they borrow'd from the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, daily robbing them at Noon day, and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away their Sheep and Cattle in Flocks and Droves. And when he had raiſed a formidable Army, and very well knew how naked and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſeleſs the Proteſtants were, (having twice before Diſarm'd them) he began palpably to diſcover how exact and punctual Obſerver he intended to be of his Oaths and Promiſes, and by the following Letters from <hi>Dublin</hi> you may ſee how he began to handle thoſe that were in his Clutches.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="margQuotes">
               <body>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48411:9"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dublin</hi> is ſurrounded for Thirty Miles about, with Popiſh Forces newly raiſed, and ſome of the ſtanding Army; all the Avenues to it are ſtopt and Guarded: So that it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to more, or travel Five Miles, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtopt and examin'd, and for the moſt part diſarm'd, diſmounted, an dpillaged. The City is filled with Soldiers, Troopers, and Dragoons, to the number of 30000. Theſe are Quartered upon private Houſes, as well as publick, and more expected dayly. Moſt Proteſtants within Forty Miles of <hi>Dublin</hi> are pillaged, robbed, and diſarm'd; the Trees and Plantations cut down, and themſelves expoſed to the Mercy of Tories, Robbers, and Servants, who are now inliſted in the Army. We believe they are ſo every where elſe, but cannot have an accompt, becauſe all Letters are opened, examined, and ſtopt, that brings any intelligence (by the Government) that does not pleaſe the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> only by chance we hear from ſome places, and find they are uſed like thoſe nearer.</p>
                  <p>There is no Trade, Buſineſs, or Money ſtirring in <hi>Dublin,</hi> but every body expoſed to the Mercy and Inſolence of Soldiers; and when Complaint is made to the Government, there is no redreſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48411:10"/>or help; all the Forces raiſed, have no Money, nor a poſſibility of being paid, and therefore muſt be left to do as they do all at preſent, to plunder and pillage whom they pleaſe; when they have done in the Country, and deſtroyed all, as they have very near done already, they will then fall a plundering the City, which we dayly fear and expect. By Order of the Lord Deputy, the County of <hi>Meath,</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Meath,</hi> are diſarmed, and their Horſes taken from them: they are do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame in the County of <hi>Dublin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They have marked all the Stables in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and can take all their Horſes in an hour; and it's hourly expected that they ſhould diſarm every Proteſtant, which they will certainly do when they are a little ſtronger.</p>
                  <p>They are dayly Baking Bisket in the Caſtle for the March of an Army; they have proveded, as it is ſaid, Field pieces: As ſoon as they have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd <hi>Dublin,</hi> it it like they will March into the <hi>North,</hi> to ſubdue the Proteſtants there. They in probability intend to ſurprize them, and in order thereunto take up all Horſes, without regard to whom they belong; nay, they threaten, not to leave ſo much as a Hackney; by which means they may be able to ſet 10000 Men on Horſeback, and March as far as <hi>Ardmaugh</hi> or <hi>Newry</hi> in two or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48411:10"/>three days. They ſtop all intercourſes with the <hi>North,</hi> both by Sea and Land; and hope to come on them unawares. It is therefore neceſſary for the Proteſtants in the <hi>North,</hi> to be ready at a days warning to receive them; to Guard well all the Paſſes of the Mountains, and Fortify them as well as they can; to make ready Proviſion of Meal and Ammunition for the Field; and if no Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition be come to them, to ſend Ships immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Money to bring it, otherwiſe they may be upon them.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Popiſh</hi> Army will have the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, from <hi>Ardmaugh</hi> to <hi>Dublin</hi> to ſupply them; and they can have Ammunition and Proviſion come to them whent hey pleaſe, and will not ſtay for them, only ſo much as may be for preſent uſe.</p>
                  <p>They are bringing Gentlemen into Plots, and Trying them upon Popiſh Oaths, by Popiſh Judges and Juries; ſo they have ſerved Captain <hi>Philips</hi> of <hi>Mullingar,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bowen</hi> the Collector, who are to be Tryed next Week at <hi>Mullingar,</hi> and will probably be found Guilty and Executed. This will only be a Leading Example to Try and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn other Gentlemen.</p>
                  <p>Every body able to remove, is going from hence; there is no body to Head the Proteſtants if there ſhould be occaſion. There are Warrants
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48411:11"/>againſt moſt of the conſiderable Men. People are ſo intermix'd, and ſo near the Government, that they dare not ſo much as meet, much leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe any thing appertaining to the Common ſafety. If therefore the Proteſtants have no help from abroad, their Ruin is unavoidable.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Feb.</hi> 22. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="italic">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ALL the Streets in <hi>Dublin</hi> are beſet with <hi>16000</hi> Men, all their Houſes are ſearched by Dragoons, and all their Horſes taken; the Lord Mayor and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men went this day through the City, Commanding all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, by four of the Clock, to bring in their Arms to their Pariſh Church; and if they left ſo much as a Bionet not brought in, if upon ſearch any were found, That Houſe ſhould be expoſed to the mercy of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>
                           <hi>Feb.</hi> the 25th. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Proteſtants in <hi>Ulſter</hi> taking notice of theſe Proceedings, and truly judging, that their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was approaching, and that they could only expect <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> fate, to be laſt be devoured, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to rouſe themſelves into ſome preparations to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48411:11"/>oppoſe a ſudden ſurprize, and with ſtour Hearts (but weak Hands) to aſſemble, and ſtand upon their Guard, and in the Eaſtern Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim</hi> to form an Aſſociation to raiſe Troops and Companies to ſecure the Frontiers, and to prevent the Incurſions of the Enemy. But as their Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were haſty, and now ay competent to their neceſſity; ſo their Retreat was as precipitate, and diſſonant from their Reſolutions. The Deputy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got together a vaſt Army, the Proteſtants in <hi>Dublin</hi> and the adjacent Counties, being diſarm'd and diſmounted; thoſe in <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Conaght</hi> plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd and pillag'd of all their Goods, Horſes, Sheep, and Cattle: he ſent down a Body of 15000 Men into <hi>Ulſter,</hi> under the Command of <hi>rich. Hamilton,</hi> whom he conſtituted Lieutenant General of the Army; and (out of a deſign, partly to terrifie, and partly to delude the deſponding Proteſtants, who hitherto had kept up their Spirits in a daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Relief from <hi>England</hi>) he made uſe of a <hi>Presbyterian Miniſter,</hi> who had a great influence upon thoſe of his Perſuaſion (whoſe number in the <hi>North</hi> was very conſiderable) and obliged him to write this following Letter to the Right Honourable the Lord Viſcount <hi>Maſſereen,</hi> a ſtrenuous Aſſerter of the Proteſtant Intereſt, and by it the greateſt Sufferer in that Province; Copies whereof were immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately diſpers'd thro the ſeveral Counties.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="margQuotes">
               <body>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48411:12"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Loghbricklan,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>March</hi> 9. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ON the 6th inſtant I was introduced by my Lord <hi>Granard</hi> into my Lord Deputy's Preſence in the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin:</hi> I have his Paſs to come and go through and back from <hi>Ulſter;</hi> and tho I have not his Excellencies direct Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, yet I will aſſure you I am at leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Lord Deputy to acquaint the Chief, and others of thoſe of the <hi>Ulſter</hi> Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with his Diſcourſe to me, which was to the effect following, to wit,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That his Excellency doth not delight in the Blood and Devaſtation of the ſaid Province: but however highly reſents their taking and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in Arms, the affronts done by them to His Majeſty's Government thereby, and by ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities done to the late Proclamation of Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency iſſued and dated —</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Notwithſtanding whereof, is willing to receive the ſaid Province into Protection, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they immediately deliver up to his Army, for His Majeſty's uſe, their Arms and ſerviceable Horſes, and provided they deliver up to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency theſe three Perſons, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>if they remain in the Kingdom, and may be had.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48411:12"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And for further manifeſtation of his Deſign to prevent Blood, is willing to grant ſafe Conduct even to the ſaid three Perſons, or any other of their Party, to and from his Excellency, and to and from Lieutenant-General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Commander of part of his Army, hereafter men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, if they intend any peaceable and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Treaty: But withal will not, upon the ſaid Account, or any other, ſtop the March of the ſaid part of his Army, no not for one hour; and if it ſhall appear in ſuch Treaty, that they took up Arms meerly for Self-preſervation, then he will pardon even the ſaid three Perſons alſo; but is hopeleſs that any ſuch thing can be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, ſeeing that many of them have already ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and received Commiſſions from the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and diſplay his Colours in the Field, as his Excellency is credibly informed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If theſe terms be not immediately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to, he will with a part of his Army fight them; which part he intends ſhall be at <hi>Newry</hi> on <hi>Monday</hi> the 11th of this inſtant; which will from thence march to <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Colerane</hi> and <hi>Londonderry,</hi> as his Excellency in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends: And that the Countrey <hi>Iriſh,</hi> not of the Army, Men, Women, and Boys, now all Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Half-Pikes and Bionets, in the Counties
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48411:13"/>of <hi>Cavan, Monagham, Tyrone, Londonderry, &amp;c.</hi> will, upon the approach of the ſaid part of the Army, and Reſiſtance thereto made, immediately enter upon a Maſſacre of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; which Force and Violence of the Rabble his Excellency ſaith he cannot reſtrain, <hi>and fears it may be greater than in</hi> 1641. Theſe are the Heads of what I can offer to you from his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency's own mouth: but I intend to be at <hi>Hills-borough</hi> to night, and there to ſtay for this night; where, if you think fit, I ſhall fully diſcourſe with you of all the particulars; whereof, I hope, you will give immediate notice to all chiefly concerned in your County and Neighbourhood, for gaining of time. I have ſent this Expreſs, that your Lordſhip may give Advertiſement by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to all ſuch as your Lordſhip thinks conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. I ſhall add no further, till I have the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſee your Lordſhip.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhip's Obedient Servant, <hi>Alex. Osborne.</hi>
                     </signed> Received the ſame Night at <hi>Antrim.</hi>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter was received at <hi>Antrim</hi> the ſame Night; and immediately the following Anſwer was returned, by the Earl of <hi>Mount-Alexander,</hi> Lord <hi>Maſſareen,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48411:13"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">We declare the utter abhorrence of the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Blood, and that we will uſe all proper Means to avoid it, but cannot conſent to lay down our Arms, which we were forced to take up for our own Defence; nor to part with our Goods by any other than legal Means; and that we are ready to appoint Perſons to treat on each Heads, as are conſiſtent with the ſafety of our Religion, Lives, and Liberty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now to convince all Mankind, that this ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Meſſage ſent by Mr. <hi>Osbourn,</hi> dated <hi>March</hi> 9. 1688 (who came with all ſpeed from <hi>Dublin</hi>) was only a Sham and Deluſion plotted by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty to amuſe the poor Proteſtants, and caſt a Miſt before their Eyes, that they might not ſee their approaching Deſtruction. Behold the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation dated at <hi>Dublin, March</hi> 7. 1688. wherein he had decreed the Ruin of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> and the exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo many Perſons from Mercy.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" rend="blackletterType" type="declaration">
               <body>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48411:14"/>
                  <head rend="roman">By the Lord Deputy and Council, <hi>March</hi> 22. 1688/9.</head>
                  <opener rend="roman">
                     <salute>TYRCONNELL.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas ſeveral Perſons in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> and the Town of <hi>Sligo,</hi> in this His Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, have entred into ſeveral Aſſociations, containing no leſs Offence than High-Treaſon; and therupon form'd themſelves into ſeveral Parties, Dividing &amp; Marſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelves into ſeveral Regiments, Troops, and Companies, Marching well armed up and down the Country, to the great Terror of the Kings Leige People, in manifeſt breach of the Law, and of the Peace of this Realm: And having reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within our ſelves to prevent the Effuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Blood, as long as it was poſſible, by uſing all peaceable Means to reduce the ſaid Malefactors to their Obedience, have of late iſſued a Proclamation, ſetting forth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48411:14"/>the ſaid Diſorders, requiring all the ſaid Parties to diſperſe, and repair to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Habitations and Callings, aſſuring every of them of His Majeſty's Pardon and Protection. And whereas we find the ſaid Offenders, inſtead of complying with our ſaid Proclamation, ſtill to perſiſt in their Wickedneſs, by continuing in actual Rebellion, breaking of Priſons, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of Priſoners, ſecured by due courſe of Law, for Robberies, Felonies, and other heinous Crunes; by ſeizing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Majeſties Arms and Ammunition, impriſoning ſeveral of his Majeſties Army, diſarming and diſmounting them, killing and murdering ſeveral of his Majeſties Subjects, pillaging and plundering the Country, and daily committing ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acts of Hoſtility; and finding no other way left to ſuppreſs the ſaid Revellion, We the Lord Deputy have cauſed a Party of his Majeſties Army, under the Command of Lt. General <hi>Richard Hamilton,</hi> to march into the Province of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> to reduce the Rebels there by force of Arms; the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence whereof cannot but be very fatal to that Country, and the Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48411:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48411:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48411:16"/>and will inevitably occaſion the total ruine and deſtruction of that part of His Majeſties Kingdom: The Conſideration whereof hath given us great diſquiet and trouble of Mind; that a Country well planted and inhabited, ſhould now, by the inſolency and traiterous wickedneſs of its own Inhabitants, be brought to ruin or deſolation, which we are ſtill willing to prevent, if any ſpark of Grace be yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the Hearts of thoſe Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, hereby declaring, notwithſtanding the many Affronts by them put upon his Majeſties Government, notwithſtanding the ſeveral Acts of Hoſtility by them hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto committed, that if they will now ſubmit and become dutiful Subjects, His Majeſties Mercy ſhall be extended to them, excepting the Perſons hereafter excepted; and in order thereunto, We the Lord-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty and Council, do ſtrictly charge and command all ſuch Perſons in Arms in <hi>Ulſter,</hi> or the Town of <hi>Sligo,</hi> forthwith to lay down Arms, and that the principal Perſons amongſt them now in the North, do forthwith repair to Lt. General <hi>Richard Hamilton,</hi> and deliver up to him their Arms,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48411:16"/>and ſerviceable Horſes, and to give him Hoſtages as an aſſurance of their future Loyalty and Obedience to His Majeſty, and that all their Adherents do deliver up their Arms and ſerviceable Horſes to ſuch Perſon or Perſons as he the ſaid Lt. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Richard Hamilton</hi> ſhall appoint to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them. And we do alſo further charge and command all the principal Perſons of other Commotions and Inſurrections in <hi>Sligo,</hi> to repair forthwith either to us the Lord Deputy, or to Colonel <hi>M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Daniel</hi> at the <hi>Boyle,</hi> and deliver up their Arms and ſerviceable Horſes, and to give Hoſtages, as Security, for their future peaceable Deportment, and their Adherents to lay down their Arms to be delivered up, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their ſerviceable Horſes, to the ſaid Col. <hi>M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Daniel.</hi> We the Lord-Deputy hereby giving ſafe Conduct to ſuch of them as will ſubmit according to this our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation. And we do hereby further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That ſuch of the ſaid Perſons as ſhall give Obedience to theſe our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, except the Perſons hereafter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, ſhall have his Majeſties Protection and Pardon, for all paſt Offences relating
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48411:17"/>to the ſaid Commotions and Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but in caſe they ſhall be to unhappy as to perſiſt in their wicked Deſigns and treaſonable Practiſes, We the Lord-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty do hereby command all his Majeſties Forces to fall upon them wherever they meet them, and to treat them as Rebels and Traitors to his Majeſty. Yet to the end the Innocent may not ſuffer for the Crimes of the Nocent, and that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittals of Human Acts may be prevented, we do hereby ſtrictly charge and command His Majeſties Army, now upon their march to the <hi>North,</hi> and all other his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Forces, that they, or either of them do not preſume to uſe any violence to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Children, aged or decriped Men, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, Plow-men, Tillers of the Ground, or to any other who in theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions demean themſelves inoffenſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without joining with the Rebels, or aiding or aſſiſting them in their traiterous Actings and Behaviours. But in regard <hi>Hugh</hi> Earl of <hi>Mount-Alexander, John</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Mazareen, Robert</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>Kingſton, Clotworthy Sherington</hi> Eſq; Son to the Lord Viſcount <hi>Mazareene,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48411:17"/>Colvil,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Rowden,</hi> Sir <hi>John Magill, John Hawkins, Robert Sanderſon,</hi> and <hi>Francis Hamilton</hi> Son to Sir <hi>Charles Hamilton,</hi> have been the principal Actors in the ſaid Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and the Perſons who adviſed and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the ſame, and inveagled others to be involved therein: We think fit to except them out of this our Proclamation, as Perſons not deſerving his Majeſties Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or Favour.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at the Council-Chamber of <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>March</hi> 7, 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>A. Fytton, C. Granard; Limerick, Bellew, Will. Talbot, Tho. Newcomen, Rich. Hamilton, Fran. Plowden.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Deputy (who till now had never kept Faith, Truce, or Promiſe) was ſtrict and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to his Word; for he ſent down his Army at the Time, and to the Place appointed, meeting with no Reſiſtance (the Proteſtants being unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of Arms and Ammunition, and not able ſo ſuddenly to imbody themſelves, or ſtem the Torrent that was ready to overwhelm them) but what was made by Sir <hi>Arthur Rowdon,</hi> who at the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48411:18"/>head of 200 Horſe, gallantly oppoſed them; till finding it impoſſible to diſpute the Paſſage of ſo great an Army by ſo inconſiderable a Force, he made a haſty, but honourable Retreat, with the loſs of a very few Men: and being met by ſome Companies of Foot, who were marching on, (but too late, and too ſlowly) to ſecond him, they alſo retreated, but in ſome Diſorder; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obſerved by the Inhabitants of <hi>Lisburn,</hi> they began immediately to fly toward <hi>Antrim,</hi> the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of which place being ſtruck with Amazement at ſo unexpected an Adventure, betook themſelves to Flight alſo, and ſo rolling on from one Town to another, the Country was univerſally ſeiſed with a panic Fear and Conſternation, hurrying their Wives and Children toward the Sea-Coaſt, leaving their Goods in their Houſes, their Stock in the Fields, and taking no Care, but to preſerve their Lives. In this Confuſion and Fright the poor Souls fled to <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and would have gone further, if the Sea had not ſtopt them. To take upon me to Deſcribe the Horror of this Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the moſt Deplorable State of the People, the Miſery, Poverty, and Diſtreſs of many thouſand good Families, and the utter Deſolation of a moſt fruitful and well-peopl'd Country, would ingage me in a Task, which no Pen can ſufficiently expreſs,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48411:18"/>nor no Art render credible, or intelligible. Let it ſuffice, that I tell you in a word, there is not this Day a Proteſtant in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that has a Gun to defend him, a Horſe to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him, a Houſe to ſhelter him, or Stock to ſuſtain him; except ſuch as have been deluded, or (miſſing of a timely Eſcape) neceſſitated to accept of Protections (which will avail the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Compliers no longer, than till the <hi>Iriſh</hi> become Maſters of the whole) or elſe ſuch as are confined within the Walls of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> who by extraordinary Courage, whetted by Deſpair, have reſiſted a powerful Army (grown inſolent by an un-interrupted Succeſs) to the Aſtoniſhment of the Beſiegers, and the ſhame of thoſe that deſerted them. And leſt any Proteſtant ſhould continue Maſter of his own Houſe, or evade an open Compliance with the Papiſts, they found a Device to reduce them to the misfortune of this Dilemma, either to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all they had to the mercileſs Invaders, or be Proſecuted as Rebels for making Reſiſtance (which un-Chriſtian courſe they had before practiſed through the Province of <hi>Munſter</hi>) to which purpoſe they ſent Summonitory Letters to the Proprietors, in one Line threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and in another wheedling, and ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48411:19"/>puzzling them with a fatal irreſolution, till either by open Aſſault, or by the cloſe Mine of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, they became Maſters of their Wiſhes: I will give you only one for an Inſtance, ſent by Colonel <hi>Gordon O Neil,</hi> Son of that Arch-Rebel Sir <hi>Phelim O Neil.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="blackletterType">
               <body>
                  <p>BY vertue of an Order granted to me by <hi>Richard Hamilton,</hi> Eſq; Lieutenant General of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Forces in the Province of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> to grant Protedions to all ſuch as will ſubmit themſelves, and lay down their Arms, and peaceably live in their own Dwellings.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are therefore, in His Majeſties Name, to Require all Perſons, ſo inclined, to come in to me, and they ſhall be Proteued in Body and Goods.</p>
                  <p>I do hereby ſummon the Gariſon of <hi>Dauſon's-Bridge</hi> and <hi>Maghrefelt</hi> to lay down their Arms, or then to be proceeded againſt as Rebels to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and to be Proſecuted accordingly.</p>
                  <closer rend="roman">
                     <dateline>Given under my hand, at <hi>Duneen,</hi> 
                        <date>this Twenty firſt of <hi>March,</hi> 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Gordon O Neil.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48411:19"/>
            <p>I had almoſt forgot to take notice to you how craftily and treacherouſly the Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> proceeded during theſe Tranſactions. For pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to ſtand in dread of an Invaſion from <hi>England,</hi> (though by the Sequel it is more than probable he had better Intelligence from thence) he over-awed and conſtrained ſome conſiderable Perſons to abuſe the Miniſters of State with a falſe Repreſentation; others he plainly threatned, That if they did not write to their Friends in <hi>England,</hi> to diſſwade them from ſending over any Forces, he would expoſe the Proteſtants, without Mercy, or Diſtinction, to the Fury of the Soldiers, and the Mercy of the Rabble. And as for the ingenious Conceit of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections, it has proved a meer Cheat, and a Trap to inſnare credulous People; I will give you one for a Precedent.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="italic">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Richard Hamilton,</hi> Lieutenant General of His Majeſty's Forces in <hi>Ulſter,</hi> do onely receive into His Majeſty's Protection, the Body and Goods of <hi>James Hunter,</hi> of <hi>Bally menag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> in the County of <hi>Antrim,</hi> Yeoman; and promiſe and oblige my ſelf, That none of the Army ſhall moleſt, or hurt him, or take any thing from him.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given under my hand, at the Camp, <date>
                           <hi>March</hi> Twenty ſeventh, 1689.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Richard Hamilton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48411:20"/>
            <p>The poor protected Man being thus noos'd, returns to his Houſe, and follows his Labour; but anon down comes the Rabble, like an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> ſweep all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and leave nothing behind them, but a naked ſtarved Family: The wretched Man makes his Addreſs to his Protector, and receives only this cold comfort, <hi>I did promiſe to protect you from the Army, that none of them ſhould offer you any Violence; but I have no power to reſtrain the Rabble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now reflect upon what has been ſaid, and briefly re-capitulate the preſſing Exigencies, the imminent Extremities, and unavoidable Dangers, to which the poor Proteſtants were ſubjected: and then I will appeal to any Man of Senſe, that is not a bigotted Papiſt, Whether they had not juſt and undeniable reaſons to ſeek their Eſcape from the impending Perſecutions, and to take Sanctuary in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>Iſle of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Sword was taken from the Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> becauſe he favoured the Proteſtants; and put into the Hands of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> becauſe he was a furious Patron of the Papiſts, was it not high time for conſiderate Men to foreſee the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal conſequences: and to avoid them by a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48411:20"/>leiſurely Receſs? when the Officers of the Army were turned out, and the Souldiers disbanded, merely becauſe they were Proteſtants: when the Majority of the Privy-Council, the Judges, Juſtices of the Peace, Sheriffs, and all other civil Officers, were avowed, and profeſt Papiſts: when ſuttle Jeſuits, mercenary Prieſts, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friers ſwarmed through the Land, and crept into all Houſes and Families, and the Idolatrous <hi>Maſs</hi> allow'd to be ſet up in every Town: when the Corporations were ſuperſeded, and none admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Magiſtracy, or Freedom, but the ſcum of the Vulgar, and the Spawn of Rebels: when the Act of ſettlement began to be can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſſed, and Mens Titles to Eſtates and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were proſtituted to the prejudicate Verdict of ſuch Jurors, packt by ſuch Sheriffs, and the partial ſentence of ſuch Judges, who all concur in accounting it a meritorious Service to weaken and deſtroy the Hereticks; was it not a raſh Madneſs, for any who had opportunity and Ability to remove themſelves, to continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the licentious and Arbitrary humors of ſuch a Government? But when Men began to ſee how they were reduced to a Neceſſity of ſuffering, whether any ſuccours arrived to them from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or whether they were delay'd; they had
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48411:21"/>no Election to make, but to contrive an eſcape from their cruelty, or their Revenge. When Men were every where alarm'd with a Deſign of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Inſurrection, and univerſal Maſſacre, he that was ſo hardy as to over-look this without a concernment, muſt have an unuſual Portion of wit, to conduct his Courage; for my Part, I am ſo far from wondring that ſo many affrighted Perſons ſhould prefer an incommodious and inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Paſſage by Sea, to ſo hazardous and terrible an abiding upon Land, that I do admire the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible ſtupidity of thoſe who ſtay'd behind. And now the Deputy having added 40000 new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rais'd Men to the ſtanding Army, 50000 of the Rabble being furniſhed with Skenes and half-Pikes, animated and ſecretly ſworn by the Prieſts to extirpate all Proteſtants, making it a national, as well as a religious Quarrel (as appears by the Motto in their Standard ſet up in the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin, Now or never, Now, and for ever</hi>) the Proteſtants in <hi>Munſter,</hi> and <hi>Conaght,</hi> turned out of their Houſes, deſpoil'd of their Goods, and plundered of their Cattle, all Armes and Horſes taken from thoſe in <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>Lemſtor:</hi> a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and inraged Army falling into the Bowels of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> ravaging without Check, or Controll, the naked, ſtript, and un-armed people flying
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48411:21"/>before them, to ſeek a ſhelter in <hi>London-Derry,</hi> which could not contain the hundredth part of thoſe that retreated to it; there was nothing to be done (to eſcape a ſuddain Deſtruction by the Sword, or a lingring Death by Famine) but to fly over Sea, and preſerve Life, which was all that was left them. As for the more unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Remnant of the Poor Proteſtants, who being either gull'd and intrapp't by Protections, and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for ſlaughter; or elſe deny'd a Licence to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelves, that they may indure the miſery, and at laſt receive the wages of Slaves and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Perſons (which aſſuredly will happen, whenſoever the Conqueſt of the Kingdom ſhall be complete, and the Government devolved on the French; or perhaps ſo ſoon as an Army from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhall land there for its reſcue) they are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with ſuch poynant Circumſtances of ſadneſs and ſorrow, that my Heart bleeds for them; and though I dare not truſt to the compaſſion or Prayers of thoſe hard-hearted Men who find fault with us for coming away; Yet I leave it to their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to determine, whether their condition be not more deſperate and deplorable, who have ſtaid behind.</p>
            <p>May the good people of <hi>England</hi> ſee, and be convinced (by the diſmal examples of <hi>Ireland</hi>) what
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48411:22"/>would have bin their portion, if Popery had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd, and a Popiſh King continued to Reign over us. May they never be deceived by that impracticable Paradox, That the Engliſh Nation and the Proteſtant Religion can ſubſiſt, or be in ſafety, under the adminiſtration of <hi>French-men,</hi> and the Dominion of a Papiſt.</p>
            <p>I have now wearied your Patience, and eaſed my own Thoughts. It ſhall be your Fault, if I be not always,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 27. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Caſe of the Oaths ſtated, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Anſwer of a Proteſtant Gentleman in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to a late Letter from <hi>N. N.</hi> upon a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> betwixt them concerning the preſent Poſture of <hi>That Country,</hi> and the Part fit for Thoſe concerned <hi>There</hi> to Act in it, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Dialogue between Two Friends, Occaſioned by the late Revolution of Affairs, and the Oath of Allegiance, by <hi>W. K.</hi> M. A. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Examination of the Scruples of Thoſe who refuſe the Oath of Allegiance, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Conſiderations touching Succeſſion and Allegiance, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
